and admitting everybody on end.
Okay, Jorge, go for it.
>> All right, I'm gonna
Good morning everyone. My name is Jorge
Gonzalez. I'm the medical psilocybin
program manager and uh we are in the
research and continuous improvement
committee with the chair Dan Jennings.
uh he will take over in just a moment
and also have a couple of guest speakers
who he will introduce. But first
remember that this meeting is being
recorded. So uh remember to keep
language appropriate as the recordings
are made public uh on our website on the
department of health website. Also
that's the other one of the other
reasons we uh also uh turn off people's
camera. We want to make sure that all
backgrounds are appropriate. The only
ones who will really have our uh the
cameras on will be uh the do staff when
necessary or uh when it's time, but also
Dan Jennings as the chair will have his
camera [snorts] on and so will the folks
who will be presenting. So with that, uh
I put that reminder in the chat with
also our contact information. Um and so
there Dan, whenever you're ready, uh
take it away.
>> Perfect. Thank you. Appreciate it. All
right. Thank you very much everybody for
being here this morning for our regular
scheduled uh research and continuous
improvement committee uh subcommittee
and appreciate y'all being here today
because today we've got a couple of
guest speakers as already mentioned and
our inter session workg group will be
reporting out on the reporting framework
recommendations to this committee so we
can gain some consensus before we move
on to the next milestone. Uh so during
this first time I would love to kind of
just remind you all for the
introductions. So here in a moment we'll
move into the introduction uh phases. So
while everybody's getting ready for that
I would love for uh the department of
health team to introduce themselves and
their staff. And while everybody is
doing that if you wanted to introduce
yourself you may raise your hand uh
using the teams. We'll call on you here
after the do introductions.
And thank you, Dan. Good morning,
everybody. I'm Dr. Dominic Zerlo and I
am the center director for medical
cannabis and psilocybin.
Um, and Brenda,
>> good morning everyone.
>> Happy Friday.
>> Oh, sorry.
>> Sorry. [laughter]
>> You go, Brenda. You go.
>> Sorry.
>> That was great. Brenda Marcenz, I am the
deputy director here at the center.
Happy Friday, everybody.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh, and then we have Cyrus.
>> Good morning everyone. I'm Cyrus. I am
the associate environmental scientist
with the psilocybin program.
>> And Leslie.
>> Good morning everyone. I'm Lesie
Peterson and I was diagn as they see the
compliance officer. Good morning.
>> And Dr. Rob.
>> Morning everybody. I'm Robert Trucker.
I'm the medical director of the program.
Glad you're all here.
And Johnny.
>> Good morning. I'm Johnny Mushe and I'm a
management analyst here with the
program.
>> And Adrian.
>> Uh, hi. Good morning. My name is Adrian
Estrada and I'm a health educator for
the center for medical cannabis and
psilocybin and occasional occasional
coffee grabber. Thank you for being
here. Happy Friday. And Kathy,
>> good morning everybody. I'm Kathy
Algeria. I'm the IT project manager that
supports the center
>> and Selena.
>> Good morning everyone. I'm Selena. I
oversee budget for the program.
And that is our team that is here
present today. So, thank you Dan. I'll
turn it back on over to you.
>> Great. Appreciate it. And before you
jump off, I just wanted to I remember
during the announcements there's uh an
upcoming education and training
committee that's coming up today at 1:00
if I'm not mistaken.
>> That is correct.
>> And that's with Brenda. So, I think what
we'll be able to do
>> Brenda Bard.
>> Yes. I was going to say Brenda. That's
me. [laughter]
So, let's open up the introductions for
everybody. I know that Kate will be
next, but Brenda, go ahead and introduce
yourself, please, and also give the uh
uh the teaser for your uh committee for
this afternoon.
>> Ah, thank you. Uh good morning,
everyone. I'm Brenda Burgard. I am a
therapist and I am the chair for
education and training. Thank you.
>> Don't forget, come to Brenda's meeting
at 1:00 today. If you've been signed up,
make sure you go to the medical
psilocybin web page.
>> Thanks for the plug.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Hey,
>> yeah, you're the next one coming up. So,
appreciate that. And then we'll move
over to everybody else with their hands
up for their introduction. Remember,
during your introduction, just let us
know your name, your location, where
you're calling in from, uh your
affiliation, if any, and if this is your
first or returning.
>> All right. And first, we've got Kate
Hawk. And Kate, your mic is enabled.
>> Good morning, everyone. Kate Hog in
Santa Fe. And I think what's relevant
for this is I'm working on research with
Scottsdale Research Institute on whole
mushrooms in their phase one FDA
studies. I'm also I see harm reduction
on there. Worked with Zeno and uh I will
be on the call uh with Brenda this
afternoon.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Kate. And next we've
got Sky Rivers. And Sky, your mic is
enabled.
Good morning everyone. Sky Rivers with
the Santa Fe Reporter sitting in. I've
been doing research on the legalization
of the psilocybin for quite some time
now. And uh the article will be out
within the next couple of weeks finally.
So thank you for having me.
>> Awesome. Thanks Sky. And next Danielle
Leonard. And Danielle your mic is
enabled and you can unmute.
And just as a reminder um for unmuting
um there's an icon at the top banner uh
that says mic um and you have to select
that and you might have to select the
drop down arrow next to it as well. Um
if uh particular microphone isn't
selected or anything.
All right. And if you're still
experiencing trouble, you can also drop
an introduction in the chat. Um or you
can try um dropping off uh and then uh
logging back into the meeting.
Okay, it looks like Danielle might still
be having some trouble. So, we'll go to
uh Hana Rose next.
And Hana, your mic is enabled and you
can unmute.
>> Good morning. My name is Hana Rose. I'm
here in Silver City, New Mexico,
and I'm a BSW student. Um so going for
social work and also a first generation
kendera and glad to be here with you all
this morning. Thank you.
>> Awesome. Thanks.
And I think that's all the hands I see
up for now. And then yeah in the chat
we've got introductions from uh James
Brown. Morning everyone. James Brown
Pharma D Five Degrees North Healing
Foundation. So happy to see uh so happy
to be here today to participate and help
out. Um and then Danielle Leonard, sorry
mic is not working. Therapist in Santa
Fe and do research with NMHU.
>> Uh Johnny, we also have a couple of
other board members who just joined us.
Ian and Desba were here. So if they want
to introduce themselves as well.
Oh, awesome. Um, let's see. And I think
you guys's mics. Oh, wait. Let me
elevate Desbot to presenter 2. Okay.
Yeah. Um, let's see. I guess we can go
to Ian.
Perfect. Good morning everyone. My name
is Ian Dunn. I am the chair of the
medical psilocybin advisory board
calling here from Rioancha, New Mexico.
Um, just happy to participate and thank
you all for being here. I'm happy to see
some familiar faces and some unfamiliar
faces. So, or I guess voices, not really
faces, but um I appreciate everyone
being here today. Thank you.
>> Thanks, Ian. Um and uh Chris Piscus.
>> Good morning, everyone. My name is Chris
Piscus. I'm a veteran and advisor board
member and I'm glad to be here. Thanks
Dan for chairing this morning and all
the work you do. Awesome.
Thanks Chris and Desba.
>> Uh y everyone uh glad to be here part of
the advisory board and uh thank you Dan
for chairing.
>> Awesome. Okay. And I think uh
right I think that's everybody.
So I'm
>> thanks appreciate. Did we get Eileen's?
Uh, hey all Eileen Brewer, Paint
Avocate, New Mexico Pan, happy to be
here. Um, and did we get Brooke reading
in from the chat also?
>> No. Let's see. Yeah. So, Brooke also um
introducing in the chat. Good morning,
Brooke here. MSN ed hospice RN studying
psychedelics for end of life interested
in research and rolling out looking to
relocate to New Mexico.
>> Great.
>> Thanks. Appreciate that. And I think
that's everybody on the announcements
and and uh introduction side. So
appreciate everybody being here,
introducing yourselves. And uh for our
agenda today, what we uh have is said we
have a special guest presentation uh
Todd Cortez with open. And then we'll
move into our inter session work uh
group report out and this will be on the
reporting framework uh the foundations
recommendations and then we'll move into
our consensus and kind of our next work
sprint which will be working on the harm
reduction and quality improvement
framework and then that should wrap us
up. So uh I just looking in the
participant list I'm not seeing Todd if
I'm not mistaken though. So Todd is
supposed to be here,
>> Dan. Uh Todd just Todd just texted me
and he said they may be running a couple
minutes late. He thought he'd be there
by 9:20 though.
>> Okay, gotcha. Well, perfect. Then we'll
kind of reorient our uh time here and
then uh we can kind of move into and
this is for Danielle. I know that
Danielle was going to be presenting on
the intersectional work report. Um and
so I know Danielle said that the
microphone's not working. So Danielle,
did you want to be able to present or
James or Gregory?
And any of y'all can if you need to
raise your hand, let us know who's going
to be taking over on this and then we'll
move into that. Great. Can yell
at
>> Daniel if you if you would like um if
you can try to uh hop off the meeting
and hop back on and see if that resolves
it.
>> And that's okay. While you're doing
that, uh, I'll go ahead and kind of give
a little bit of a background from our
last meeting. Uh, most of you probably
were here at that meeting, but if you
weren't, so this will just be kind of a
kind of refresher. Is that, uh, our, uh,
research and continuous improvement
committee has really three
responsibilities. We have a reporting
framework responsibility, as I said, the
harm reduction and quality improvement,
uh, framework responsibility, and
finally a core and extended data set uh,
framework responsibility. So we have
organized uh everybody that comes to
these meetings into three different
intersectional work groups and that's
the care pathway and safety work group,
the participant experience and fit work
group and the data reporting
architecture work group. And so uh three
people have been pretty instrumental in
leading that. Uh Gregory Evans, uh James
Brown, and of course Danielle Leonard.
And so these three groups have been
working outside of these regular
meetings that we have and then report
back. So this first report out will be
talking about the reporting framework.
These will be kind of some of the things
that the work group will respond on is
that each one of these uh work groups
has kind of a role and responsibility uh
as it relates to bringing in the
reporting framework. Uh so so today
we'll hear from them a little bit more
about what they've kind of come to a
group work on and then later on we'll
come to that kind of consensus building.
So and then whenever uh Todd and his
team come on then we'll be able to bring
them in for their presentation from the
Oregon Silicon Experience Network.
>> All right. And we'll do one final check
uh for Danielle. Um what are you seeing
on your screen with the mic icon when
you try to click that?
Looks like she jumps back off again.
[clears throat]
Yeah, one of the other issues if people
are joining in from
>> I'm on there we go. Sometimes uh just as
a note if people are joining in from
other largecale networks. Sometimes
those individual networks also have
restrictions for chat andor uh
microphone functions. And unfortunately
there's not anything that we from the
department can do about it. But
Danielle, I'm glad you were able to
activate your mic and I'll turn it on
over to you.
>> Um, thank you. Hi. I'm wondering um if
yes, there's probably enough time. Let
me share the screen. I just want to
throw up a table.
And I've got a couple of hands up. So, I
just before you move on, I know that
Greg Evans has got hands up, but Dr.
Trucker's got his hand. So, um,
>> Dr. Do you have anything? If if I may
interrupt quickly, I I think Todd is
trying to log on. Um Johnny, can you
help that help him do that or can you
see him at all?
>> No, he's he's not in the lobby. So um
but I [clears throat] can if you send me
his email, I can just send him a uh
presenter link um and he can try to get
in that way if he's having issues.
>> All right. Excellent. I'll try to do
that right now. Thanks.
appreciate that. And then and we'll go
ahead and uh lean over to Gregory Evans
uh hand up so confidence as well.
>> Awesome. And uh your mic is enabled now,
Greg.
Oh, so right out. So you have the same
issue as well. Um, have you jumped out
of the meeting and come back in?
Um, I I have my mic's working, but I'm
not able to share the screen at this
point. And I'm also thinking it sounds
like Todd is probably going to start in
a couple of minutes anyway.
So perhaps we should wait.
Okay.
Um
All right.
And uh while while we wait for hopefully
Todd's coming in a little bit so I'll
introduce a little bit about Todd.
Todd's a key figure at open which is the
Oregon psilocybin experience network. Um
they have practice-based research
platform that has been embedded in
Oregon's state licensed psilocybin
program since launch and open has been
systematically collecting real world
outcome data from service recipients
across Oregon building an impressive
evidence base on what psilocybin
assisted services actually look like at
scale in a regulated setting. And so and
just like that Todd pops up on the
screen and that was perfect that was
absolutely perfect timing. So, thank you
very much for being here and uh I
apologize. I hope I have not butchered
your name. So,
>> no, thank you, Dan. I really appreciate
the invite and uh and and and uh thank
you all for doing the service that
you're doing. I'm just pulling up uh my
presentation and I'll dive in and um I'm
curious if uh my co-director Ad Ray is
on. I It took me a while to get the
registration straightened out here.
Let's see. I'm glad you're here. Thanks
for being here. We were kind of bouncing
between, so we were like, we'll just
jump to the next thing while you're
coming in. And then so I think we've all
got the technical issues. Almost kind of
worked out, but uh looks like Adrian is
here present, but unable to use mic or
camera. So it's Adrien Wilson Poe. Is
that correct?
Is that your co-presenter?
>> Yeah. Um, yes.
>> Yes, I'm here. Thank you. Someone
enabled my mic. Yes, thank you.
>> Okay, wonderful. And I'm just sharing my
screen now.
Um,
okay. [sighs] Let's see.
All right.
Uh, can you all see a slide that says
the psychedelic data disconnect?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Okay. Let me see if I can enlarge that.
Are you seeing presentation view?
>> Uh, this is just your a slide deck on
the left side along with the main.
>> Oh gosh. Okay.
Do you have it in presenter view in a
different screen?
>> Yeah, let me uh back out of this.
>> It's okay. You can just share. You can
back out of the share and then share
again and to that screen.
>> Thank you.
>> Think in teams you just see a small
thumbnail of the main slide and that way
you could select that one I believe.
>> I appreciate that.
>> Yeah.
Uh it's back to the uh it's back to the
the PowerPoint. what
the slide deck itself and along with the
slides on the left but if you would like
you can definitely present from that
side.
Okay, let me uh
All right, let's try this again.
Thank you for your patience.
>> Boy, I have given so many of these
presentations. I don't know why this
morning is challenging.
Um,
>> yeah, I think that everybody had a
little bit of challenge this morning
with this. So, now now we're seeing an
email. So,
>> okay, let me uh
>> But if you want, you can just
>> one more time here.
[laughter]
Um,
yeah, and Gregory, you're exactly right.
Something isn't nature today.
Hey, okay, we see one slide.
Okay. Excellent. In presentation mode.
>> Yes. Just one second.
>> All right. So, I will dive again. Thank
dive in. Thank you um everybody for your
patience. Uh one of the challenges u
that that we're all encountering is
something that I call the psychedelic
data disconnect. Right? On the one hand,
we've got these wonderful clinical
trials that showed few safety events and
observational studies that show few
safety events. And on the other hand, we
have millennia of indigenous practices
to suggest uh that this is a value to
communities and uh with with not a lot
of red flags and efficacy in clinical
trials. What we don't know is
let's see this isn't changing in your
view, is it? The animations aren't
working.
>> No, we still see the psychedelic data
disconnect.
>> Okay.
Um, I'm just going to
give up on uh sharing screen um and
uh that way and just um show the
presentation. I don't know why it's not
working. Um
all right.
Okay. Can you see my uh just this the
screen the
>> Are you seeing anything?
>> Nothing
at this moment.
>> Okay, I'm just going to present from the
the PowerPoint presentation itself on
the slides.
Uh
if you've got it up and could do better,
go for it. Um, okay. Can you see this
slide?
>> Something up.
>> Uh, the psychedelic data connect with
disconnect with the
state regulated settings at the bottom.
>> Nothing else except for the two circle
safety and effectiveness.
>> Oh gosh. Okay.
Okay.
Um,
what about that?
>> Nothing has changed yet.
>> I swear I give hundreds of these. Um,
>> completely understand.
>> If you want, you might just be able to
share that main screen that you have of
your PowerPoint that you present from.
>> Yeah, that's what I'm trying to do. Is
that sharing? Well, it's back to the
same single slide.
>> Let's just go with that. We're gonna go
with that. Okay. So, what So, the very
slick animation here.
>> Hold on a second. Somebody's coming in.
>> Sorry, Todd. This is Jorge from the
Department of Health. If you want to
email that to us, then I could I could
uh handle it on this end and it might
work out for you better if that's what
you want to do. That's an option.
>> I appreciate that so much, Jorge. I will
email the PDF to the group afterward.
And let's just charge ahead here. U
because I I know how valuable your time
is and I don't want to eat into this. Um
the the the very slick animations that
normally flow smoothly. We're trying to
make this point. We know all of this
stuff from the past, but we don't know
how all this plays out in state
regulated settings because we don't have
much data on it. And that is why we
formed open. Um okay.
And can you see an did the slide advance
to something called psychedelic data
insured resources?
>> Todd, this is a disaster.
>> Todd, do you want me to see if I can
share mine?
>> I guess so. Sure.
>> All right.
Thank thank you in the meantime while
lady's um trying to pull this up. Um
uh for for serving on this panel um you
know I I uh did the same thing in the
first four years of the Oregon measure
109 roll out and it's so much work. I
know how much work you're putting in and
how many hours and um you know served
both on the full board and the co-chared
the research committee and um so thank
you. I I I really feel the
the amount of work you're doing.
So you'll have to forgive me. This is
essentially the same um presentation but
for a different group. Um
uh oh, now it says that it shouldn't
couldn't share my content.
I'll try one more time.
>> Yeah. And while you're working um
Todd, can you uh topline Open's mission
statement? Just tell us a little bit
about what Open's all about.
>> Sure. Yeah. O open we formed Open to
fill this data gap, right? And uh it was
it was clear that um at the time very
early on there wasn't a lot of of work
being done. And so we sort of just
stepped in a group of like-minded
community researchers and university
based researchers and developed a system
um to u uh document what was happening
uh to the best of our abilities. Um we
have a philosophical uh uh sort of
baseline and that's that uh we view data
as a natural resource not as something
to be owned or uh collected uh purely
for scientific reasons. Um uh and uh for
that reason we purposely did not set
this up as a commercial entity. Um it's
meant to be open and shared with uh
public health uh parties with
researchers around the country. Um and
uh we're actually just getting ready to
publish our very first quantitative
paper of the Oregon experience. Um
u and have have uh done a lot more as
well. Um the system was designed in
partnership with our uh state's uh
clinical and translational science award
or CTSA. Um University of New Mexico has
one I'm sure um and what this does is
open the possibility for some highlevel
engineering and support. And so rather
than take an off-the-shelf platform like
Qualrix or something else, um we heard
from the community how much they prior
prioritized privacy and customization
and adaptability, those three things.
And the NIH funded engineers then
developed this homegrown product called
open um that can be accessed from any
platform um uh via the web and uh is
really adhering to the very very highest
standards of data encryption and
privacy. Um and we designed a system to
be able to follow people prospectively
longitudinally over time. Um in such a
way that they remain anonymous actually
um their their their um names um don't
don't appear in the follow-up. They're
assigned a unique number and that
follows them through. even if they go to
a second facilitator for a second or
third session somewhere else um that
person is is still tracked within the
system for 12 months. Um
uh
so that that's that's uh kind of where
we're at. Um so far um the slides uh are
from last month and so so uh uh they uh
the most recent data is that we have 523
individuals enrolled. We launched a
pilot in Colorado about four five months
ago now um just as they were starting to
open some of their healing centers. And
so we have a rapidly growing number of
folks um in Colorado. Uh the way it
works is we reach out first to the
facilitator community and spend a lot a
lot a lot of time doing community
building, right? And understanding what
uh the community of facilitators is
looking for, what they need, what they
want. Um and then participation is
voluntary c um in in Colorado and
Oregon. um such that a facilitator uh
who wants to join the consortium
uh joins they complete a very short
baseline survey of their own training
and characteristics and um u
you know things like this um less than
five minutes and then they're registered
as research participants themselves. Um
the reason this is important is because
we have a federal certificate of
confidentiality
uh which are really challenging to to
get actually uh in in the current
landscape. Um, and what that does is
completely protects both the facilitator
and their client from subpoena of
federal, state or local judges or or
whatever. That that data can never be
accessed um uh with a legal order. So
that that's why we set it up that way.
Um at any rate, the facilitators then
offer their uh participation to their
clients via a secure link and their
clients then can opt in um and they
complete a brief online consent form. Uh
we set it up as a research study rather
than
um
uh
it's somewhere between a research study
and a registry actually. Um but we we
decided to have people consent again
hearing from the community about their
concerns about privacy and
confidentiality
um and u uh making sure that whatever
data they shared would be utterly
confidential. I see um uh Ian maybe um
has has their hand up.
>> Yeah. So I just had a a question. Um, so
you had mentioned the complete
confidentiality and I think that patient
privacy is incredibly important. My
concern is what happens when there is a
facilitator that acts poorly and we're
trying to get those medical records. If
they can't be subpoenaed by a court, how
would a patient ever be able to prove
what treatment they underwent?
>> That's a wonderful question. There there
are two parallel systems. there's the
data that they're reporting in the
system in open that's the only thing
that's protected. Um so I if if they're
entering anything in electronic health
record in um whatever Alia Osmine
Homecoming um uh th those those uh
practice management platforms and EHRs
don't have uh uh that federal
certificate of confidentiality and uh a
lawyer would be able to access those
records if they're being kept. I think
that's really interesting in the case of
New Mexico where the plan, my
understanding is the plan is to be much
more integrated into FQC's and the
health care system. Um it would function
basically like any other medical legal
case. I I would imagine I suppose there
are people on this call that know more
about uh the legalities of this than I
do.
>> So what I'm hearing so like open would
just be for like the research part data
collection. It's not like an overarching
system. Okay, cool. Thank you.
>> Um, no, we we we decided to keep it
separately because there there are two
flavors of data that one can collect,
right? One is
something along the lines of EHR data uh
that you can build a registry on, which
is powerful in its own right, and you
can get data on pretty much everybody in
your population. It's usually an opt
out. Um or just this is part of
receiving services and your data is
there. Um
that that's good as far as it can go,
but it only reflects experiences that
are recorded in that electronic health
record, right? So if somebody has three,
four integration visits with their
therapist, for example, after their
session and then they never see them
again, that's it. That's all the the the
data that you can collect. Um a
longitudinal cohort study which is open
um really gets the the individuals
permission to to keep following them. Um
and we have all of these automated
built-in uh reminders to be able to do
that. Um so um so uh we the the
individual regardless of whether or not
they're still engaging with the
facilitator
um continues to uh be pinged and uh
supply uh data u moving forward. Um and
and some of this is quite sensitive,
right? We're asking them to dep to rate
their depression and anxiety and
um other clinical measures
um um some some pretty sensitive issues
u which is why the privacy um and that
way you know what happens in the 12
months afterwards. And so far um uh
we're really proud of our retention
rate. the so far we've had 87% of people
continue to complete um uh surveys at
all seven data points. Um so that's
before their experience, one week after
their experience,
one month after their experience and
then 3, six, 9 and 12 months after their
experience.
um greater than 87% uh response at each
each point.
Um
Greg.
>> Oops. Okay. Yeah. Um
>> it works. I guess
>> um since you're on that point curious
where you see the greatest attrition
and then total program participants for
the state, what percentage are you
seeing engage in your data study?
>> So the the greatest attrition so far
seems to be a little bit random. um we
haven't done an in-depth analysis, but
um I if if you look at cohort studies
that follow people long term, um you're
doing really really great if you can get
75%
maybe 80%
and and so we're kind of actually
knocking the ball out of the park. um
way exceeding standards uh for attrition
and um and and it's it's most likely
random. I don't know if D 80 has a
better response to that, but um the the
second um the the second question
though, there was two questions in
there. Um and the second was
>> representiveness. Yeah,
>> representiveness. So um so Oregon, we
started collecting data in Oregon long
before um the SP303 passed and and the
state started collecting basic numbers
of people having experiences. When they
started doing that during the same time
frame, we're uh we're hitting about 11%
of the population of people receiving
services in Oregon. Um that may sound
low. Um, however, uh, again, from a
public health standpoint, 10% of any
population is astounding. Um, the CDC
would would, uh, would love to see that.
Um, um, it is a convenient sample. Um
but what we've done is go back and
analyze
uh the extent to which the open cohort
uh approximates the broader cohort of uh
the the people receiving state services
and uh so far it tracks quite closely in
terms of demographics,
psilocybin dose and to the extent that
the state collects uh information on
serious adverse events. um uh comparable
there as well. Um
>> I mean I can just keep asking questions.
>> Fantastic. We we can also talk about
results uh if that's helpful. And now
I'm I'm regretting not sending the
slides to Jorge. Um, but uh you still
can.
>> Yeah, I I I don't have your email. I
don't think
>> I sent the slides over. We have some
result slides that should be in your
inbox.
>> Okay,
>> I will check that. I will check that.
Thank you, Adrian.
>> I think Robert has his hand up.
Bob,
>> hi Todd. Just a question.
[clears throat]
>> I think your boom is up on your mic.
>> It always is, isn't it? Um Todd, you're
following people out for 12 months. I
know we've had this discussion. You plan
on following them longer, right? This is
You're not stopping at 12 months or are
you stopping?
>> Right now, our funding allows collection
out to 12 months. We would love to
collect data longer. If New Mexico were
interested in that, it's an easy add-on.
Um and the costs of following longer are
incremental. uh most of the costs are in
the first few months.
>> And I should also say that in our most
recent grant application to the NIMH, so
our our we have one grant that's funded
through NAIDA, but the other one through
NIMH, which was recently submitted, does
indeed follow up proposed to follow up
for 24 months.
>> Okay. And we also in our state, we have
four medical conditions
that we are following or four qualifying
conditions. Is your tool adaptable to
follow these populations?
>> Yes, absolutely. Um, we already actually
track individuals
um with depression, anxiety, and PTSD,
three of the four. Um, we we also ask
about um intentions for use around um
issues of death. Um but uh we would need
to
put in some some more specific measures
for the fourth category of adult life
care. That did I get those four
categories correct?
>> Yes. And is it sounds like your programs
you can alter it easily. So if we wanted
to do end of life questions you could
modify it reasonably easily to capture
that data.
>> Yeah. Absolutely. And that was one of
the reasons AD and I really decided to
uh go for the custom build. Makes it
very nimble and adaptable.
>> And I know that Ian's got his hand up
for next question.
>> Perfect. And then uh just one
correction. Instead of anxiety, we have
um substance use disorder. So it might
be important.
>> Substance use disorder. I did get that
wrong of course. So, you know, my day
job is an addiction researcher. So,
I don't know how I got that right, but
um uh name we actually did also just
receive an NIH award from the National
Institute on Drug Abuse.
>> Um and that's allowing us to really
build out the substance use questions as
well. Um so that um um Okay. So, Ay, you
got your slide deck. Do you have the the
results on this slide deck?
>> That's me. Uh Jorge, which page do you
want it on?
>> Uh these are 80 slides.
>> Yeah. Scroll down past slide 11.
Probably toward slide 15 or so.
You're going um
>> slide 13.
>> If you could tell me the title, I could
look for that of the page. Um, one more
slide down as a good
Oh, that's facilitator. Keep going.
>> I I can see your slides, can other
people?
>> Yeah, I'm not driving them.
>> I am.
>> Oh,
that's probably a good place to start is
with participant safety. So, it's slide
17, participant reported safety.
right there.
>> Yep.
>> Okay.
>> Todd, do you want to keep going?
>> Um, you know what? Uh, these are your
slides. Mine are slightly different. Why
don't you go for it?
>> Sure.
>> Yeah, you bet. Um, so when we
the the concept of what does it mean to
have a safe service is still quite
nebulous. So what we are doing right now
the way that we collect safety data
which is ever evolving and and becoming
more and more nuanced is triangulating
information that's coming from the
client perspective as well as from the
facilitator perspective. So on the
facilitator side we ask about acute
events that happen inside the session.
So that would be something like um the
person needed medical attention or was
reported uh or sorry was uh transported
to emergency services. But we're also
asking participants for their own
subjective perceptions of safety. Um and
we do this at every follow-up time
point. So you can see that um the most
common um perceptions of you know
negative impacts were feeling sick for
more than one day and having new
headaches that lasted more than one day.
everything else that shows up um in
terms of participant reported safety,
you know, is right around the the 1%
mark. Um two things that we are watching
closely though is whether or not
symptoms are worsening. And so, um in
this case, we're looking at depression
and anxiety symptoms that that might be
worsening. Um one question that we get
asked often is what is happening with
suicidal ideiation? Uh so we we have
again a a few different places on the uh
surveys where we're asking folks about
suicidal ideiation. Um but this is
something that we're um watching really
closely to to see how that changes over
time and how we how we can do an an even
better job of increasing the resolution
of that question. Uh next slide please.
Um Todd, I'm going to pass it over to
you. I think you do a really good job
talking about our serious adverse
reactions.
>> Thanks AD. Um the bottom line is we've
uh we we mapped our definition of
serious adverse reactions to the Oregon
Health Authority definition of requiring
uh some sort of medical or mental health
intervention. So, so far we've had about
1% a little less than 1% or four
individuals
um uh experience serious adverse
reactions. All of them have been
behavioral reactions, not medical
reactions. We haven't had any serious
adverse medical reactions. Um all of
them, there are a few themes here. All
of them occurred in psychedelic naive
individuals
um seeking services for mental health
issues that they had not um found
resolution for for other um uh problems.
Um, and you can see here, um, I won't
read all of these, but, uh, the dose was
quite high actually, uh, for at least a
couple of those clients. Um, uh, and,
um, uh, yet um, even even with this, two
of the four clients ranked the
experiences among the most meaningful of
their lives um, and said their goals
were met, etc., etc. had positive things
to say. One week later, um, uh, two of
the clients continued to experience on
and report ongoing psychological
difficulties. Um, and, um, both of these
had
pretty substantial pre-existing
difficulties.
>> So, you can advance to the next slide. I
think the the takeaway there is that,
you know, safety is really nuanced. So
having aggregate safety data that's you
know sort of averaged across all of the
service centers and service providers um
doesn't exactly give us that nuance that
although a person may have gone to the
emergency department they also
experienced you know one of the most
[clears throat] you know meaningful
experiences of their lives. So I think
it really highlights the real necessity
for this you know patient level
longitudinal data collection.
Um go ahead and advance to the next
slide.
So, this is where we'll jump into some
of our preliminary um mental health
outcomes. Um these have all been um
submitted to a journal and we literally
just got comments on um the submission.
So, we'll be packaging that up in the
next couple of weeks to to resubmit. Um
so, the first thing that we'll look at
here is depression. So, this is all
comers. This is not just looking at
people who came in with moderate to
severe depression but looking at you
know [clears throat] everyone in the
cohort. Um and so what we see is a sub
substantial reduction in um uh
depression symptoms and that that um
symptom reduction uh persists for up to
3 months. Um toward the end of the year
we'll have a nice follow-up study that
will you know look at a 12-month
follow-up uh as well. So we're really
excited to see uh the durability in
these findings. So you know at baseline
roughly 41% of the people in our cohort
came in with symptoms and that's at 16%
at 3 months. Next slide.
Similarly if we look at anxiety symptoms
roughly half the population came in with
moderate to severe anxiety. That goes
down at 1 and 3 months. Um and we're
excited to see how that might persist
over time as well. Next one.
And we see a similar pattern with PTSD
symptoms. So 50% of the people come in
with moderate to severe PTSD symptoms
and that reduces uh significantly to 20
and 80% at 1 and 3 months respectively.
Next slide.
On the other side of the coin, we're
also not just looking at the reduction
in mental health symptoms. We're looking
at a holistic picture of well-being. Two
of the data points that we're looking at
in that more holistic picture are mental
well-being and life satisfaction. So for
both of these measures, we are seeing a
significant statistically significant
improvement in well-being and
satisfaction. Um and again that seems to
persist out to 3 months. Next slide
please.
Todd, do you want to talk about our
limitations?
>> Sure. This is an observational study.
Currently, the data we're presenting are
uncontrolled. So, it's just pre-post.
Um, and that limits causal inference.
Um, however, uh, you got to start
somewhere, right? And, uh, this is
actually the the richest data that
anybody's been able to collect so far.
um and and rapidly growing um and very
systematically rigorously collected um
with um with careful ethics and um IRB
oversight. Um as I said earlier, the the
population represents about 10% of the
total clients receiving services in
Oregon so far. We'll see how that pans
out in Colorado. Um but the demographics
are comparable and actually we've had uh
clients from um this is this is um uh an
older number now we're over 95% of the
service centers in Oregon. Um so we do
have representation around the state
that way. Um and of course we really
can't comment on anything but the state
regulated program experience here. We're
not commenting on uh uh use in religious
ceremonies or indigenous practices or
recreational or anything else. Um u that
being said, we do have IRB approval for
all of that as well. Uh if people are
interested in that, uh we just have been
focusing on the state programs.
Um so next slide.
Um,
you want to bring us home?
>> Yeah. So, I think that um I hope at
least that what we've conveyed today um
gives you some idea of how this
realworld tracking um within the
regulated system can be helpful for
informing best practices um shaping
revisions to policy um and of course
improving the informed consent process
for clients who are seeking services. um
you know this confidential outcome
tracking is near and dear to our heart
um and as Todd mentioned you know our
IRB protocol is very broad it's
completely agnostic to geography lensure
or the substance so even today right now
we can accept people who are offering
services in the unregulated space in
Colorado um there's an interesting use
case there where you know licensed
facilitators are able to legally provide
services at home for patients with um
you know end of life issues for example.
Um NRB protocol also allows us even
today to um track other substances like
Ibgain. Um the great news about our
early findings is that they are very um
they map very well onto the findings of
that are coming out of clinical trials.
So in terms of the um impact we're
seeing in the real world and the
efficacy we're seeing in clinical
trials, it appears very similar. Um and
the safety appears the safety profile is
is really beneficial. So so we're
encouraged by the fact that our safety
looks similar to the state you know
tracking systems for safety events um
and that there there are um few safety
events happening. Um, one of the, uh,
you know, what we've shown you here
today is some of our mental health
symptoms. Of course, like we have a huge
battery, um, including substance use
questions that, um, we simply have not
had the bandwidth to to, uh, analyze in
depth yet. Um, so there's, you know, as
soon as this primary outcomes paper is
published, there's essentially three
other papers that will be unlocked by
our ability to cite that paper,
including something that's near and dear
to my heart, which is pain. So, um,
we're seeing some really encouraging
things that are happening with sematic
pain symptoms being reduced, um, you
know, out to the three-month mark. Um,
and of course, you know, like we
mentioned before, mental health symptoms
and pathology are only one way of
looking at the impact of these real
world services. Um, the other way that
you could look at it is what's happening
to this whole human. So, uh, we're
really encouraged to see, uh, what's
going to happen with life satisfaction,
well-being, spirituality, connectedness,
and a lot of the other, um, measures
that we haven't yet had the time to
analyze. Um, everything else is sort of,
uh, just wrapping up and and, um, uh,
some more conclusions. So, we'd be I
think this is a a good time to stop the
presentation and address questions.
>> Perfect. Thank you so much. Yes, I know
that there's probably plenty of people
out here that would like to ask y'all
some questions. So, and if you are,
please raise your hand.
>> See, I see Ian's hand up. Um Ian, you
can unmute.
>> All righty. Thank you guys so much for
your presentation and all the work you
guys are doing in the psilocybin space.
it is um and other substances come to
be. But um it's I have no complaints. I
just really wanted to thank you guys for
everything you shared with us and all of
the work you are doing. Um even if you
don't get to see, you know, a patient
face to face tell you thank you, the
work being done is helping people. So I
I just wanted to say I appreciate you
from the bottom of my heart.
>> Thank you.
>> Gosh, that is so kind. Thank you. Yeah.
And then I'll go ahead and speak for
Gregory Evans in the chat. He said, "How
is Oregon handling the dosage protocols
for pain management? Is there a use case
where mid-range doses are
self-administered?"
>> Yeah, in the Oregon model, there is no
self-administration. So, in our
regulated system, um the the product has
to be transferred directly from a lency
um to a client inside of a service
center. So there is no um
self-titration.
Um pain is th this is talk about like
a field that's in its true infancy. We
have absolutely no idea um you know what
the dose response might be with
psilocybin and and pain relief. One of
the things that we thought might be
happening is that for about 80% of the
people who experience chronic pain, they
also have a mood disorder like
depression. So we came into analyzing
our data from the lens of okay if these
folks have depression when their
depression symptoms resolve then their
pain will resolve and that was not borne
out in the data. So there appears to be
separate effects for psilocybin's impact
on mood in some people and psilocybin's
impact on pain in other people. What are
those factors? Is it dose? Yes. Is it
the type of pain? Maybe. Is it the
magnitude of pain? Maybe. Is it the
other um you know pain medications that
a person's taking? Maybe. So um what I'm
excited about with the pain data is the
fact that we now have enough of a
smoking gun to launch you know 10
different PhD students on their entire
careers. Um so it's an excellent
question and we have absolutely no idea
how to answer that right now.
I I would expand that that 10 PhD
students also to our colleagues in New
Mexico who we're already actually
collaborating quite closely with in
terms of uh uh University of New Mexico
with Larry Leman and Kim Paige my
counterpart for the NIDA clinical trials
network
um and there but um uh if if New Mexico
were interested and formally you know
moving forward with something like open
data collection. Um again where there
are multiple plays on our our title open
one is open science and open access and
we welcome collaborations with our
University of New Mexico partners.
Thanks. If you if any of you are in
Portland actually for the CPD meeting uh
starting Saturday, uh uh come see 80 and
Larry and I presenting on the state
models
>> and from the chat there's too from
Eileen there's good evidence for
psilocybin and cluster headache and
psilocybin migraine and also there are
many people doing studies on things like
fibromyalgia, low back pain, phantom
limb there's also foundational research
and about 20 other pain conditions and
then Gregory Evans has has his hand up.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Sorry, I'm just uh multitasking.
Um, thank you uh for presenting this.
I'd love to talk to you guys a lot more.
Um, I'm super interested in the concept
of open data share and open access. I
have a passion project that I call the
open data silo that's basically started
with HLC data and breaking that open for
public research. Um, so you're right
right in my heart. [laughter]
Um but from the
perspective of your organization and
moving forward into expanded regulated
markets and out like um wild data that's
inside containers, right? Like this is
not research data but it is researching
wild data. This is fascinating and and
pioneering. um what does your
organization
need the most to hold it? And also
curious how you're structured. Are you
nonprofit? And how's the organization
structured?
>> We're definitely nonprofit. Uh we're way
nonprofit. Um
broke. [laughter]
>> Exactly. The entity open is housed at
Oregon Health and Science University. um
even though we're uh we have broad
community collaboration.
Um so it it functions pretty much like
other um university based uh research
studies. You know, we need funding to
keep the lights on um to uh reprogram
and retool um surveys to tailor to
specific needs. um and uh ongoing
analytic uh support and and and
scientific staff time.
>> Thanks.
>> And any I would add one more thing also
that's actually the most important
thing. Uh we need
real community relationships. The reason
this is working in Oregon and Colorado
right now is we've spent a tremendous
amount of time partnering with people on
the ground there and really learning
from our friends and um that's that's
prerequisite to everything we've said I
think for any other state.
>> Yeah. And if you don't mind I'll wax
poetic on that. Like I think when we're
talking about integration and and what
real healing looks like it's community-
based. It's about having people there to
support you. And as an organization, I
think being able to partner and and
build together with additional systems
is massively important for the entire
ecosystem.
Um, so yeah, um, [clears throat] I'll
kind of leave it there, but I just
wanted to thank you so much for the
work. I think it's beautiful.
>> Yeah,
>> thank you.
>> So appreciate it, Addy and Todd, for
coming. And I think uh really I got to
give a shout out to like Danielle and
the team because getting you all here
was fantastic. I appreciate this. I
think it's been a really great
presentation to us and so now we know a
lot more about and I hope that there's
more follow-ups from this conversation.
Um so I really appreciate that. Uh
you're free. Please stick around. Uh if
you do happen to have to jump off, do
not press that big yellow button to
whatever you have to do. Sorry, Dan. I
have one more question.
>> That's the self-destruct button. And
Gregory's got one more question.
>> Okay. So, I think one of the ways that
we engaged with you was um through
conversations about um adapting Pitzky's
work. Can you talk about how you deal
with um uh PATE and how you incorporate
those instruments into your surveys?
>> Roman and and um AD and I are whole
group have been collaborating for a very
long time. my support Roman as a
co-mentor on his career development
award um and uh and he gave us early
advice on particularly we have a
spirituality major that tracks over time
um and u he he was very instrumental in
advising on that as one of his primary
interests um in terms of the pat um it's
a pretty comprehensive in-depth u uh
instrument and he's the better one to
speak to that. Um uh we chose not we've
in open we've tried to be very
parsimmonious and uh nimble. Um our
longest survey is um under 15 minutes uh
to complete. Um
and and so we've tried to avoid really
long surveys. Um what we do though is we
partnered with him on a screener
question about harms and if somebody
says that they've experienced a harm um
then they are referred assuming they've
consented to additional research um
directly to his study. Um so it's sort
of open is feeding um that scientific
work uh that that he's doing which is
crucial. I envision a time eventually
when rigorous psychometrics are done on
on the uh lengthy survey that that
perhaps the the PT will shrink uh to
something that could be more nimble in a
population-based survey.
>> Yeah. And if I could if I could add a
little bit to that, you know,
challenging experiences referral. um
some of the questions that we've been
getting from the community providers um
you know both in Oregon and Colorado and
the these concerns and questions are
coming from folks who have a background
in clinical trials and so for them you
know their concern was how are you
tracking adverse events and um you know
and and they're looking at this through
the way that we track and report adverse
events in clinical trials. Um so you
know as a observational cohort we we
don't have that capacity really like
you've seen that the safety data that we
do have and it is very you know high
fidelity and very nuanced but it's not
the same as reporting something to the
FDA in terms of an adverse event in a
clinical trial. So, we do have a number
of other mechanisms in place like Todd
mentioned the referral out to Roman's
long-term, you know, challenging
experiences study. We also have HTML
warnings, you know, in place embedded
within the software platform where if
people, you know, are reporting suicidal
thoughts, there's, you know, um the uh a
reminder to call 988 and that resources
are available. um if they have you know
experienced some other kind of
challenging or unoured event. There are
numerous places in the platform where
people are provided with the opportunity
to report compliance violations to the
state of Oregon or Colorado
respectively. So to the to the extent
that it's possible for us to encourage a
person to report those events
voluntarily, we've given them plenty of
opportunities to do that.
um you know but the nature of our work
is observational so you know there's we
we are limited in terms of you know what
we can require people to do
>> well thank you that's super helpful
>> thanks
appreciate very much and actually we're
moving right on into the next thing
which is the reporting framework that
the inter session group has been working
on and I think that that Danielle has
sent over to Jorge the the table that
she wants to present with. And so I'll
go ahead stop sharing and let uh or
bring that up if you wouldn't mind.
>> I sure have it. Okay.
>> Um hi. That was just so wonderful. Thank
you, Todd and Addie.
Can you hear me?
>> Hi. Can you Yes. Okay. Fantastic. All
right. Well, um Dan provided uh the
committee with a wonderful rich detailed
inventory of data elements and reporting
requirements um that he's uh collected
from through throughout the committee
meetings um and uh asked the three
people together in three work groups to
help come up with a framework. Um so
our our work group uh has uh
taken a few steps back to come up with a
uh something to hang all this
information on. And what made the most
sense was
um to have the backbone uh follow the
client's path throughout the program. So
the framework that we've come up with uh
follows the client through from referral
assessment
uh you can see in the workflow stage
column here uh preparation
administration and early followup
integration and then outcome monitoring.
So information gets collected at the
point of care where it naturally arises
um and by the person best positioned to
provide it. Um there's a few principles
worth u mentioning uh from the paper
that we submitted. Uh one guiding um
principle would be to collect
information once and use it many times.
Um, as Todd and Addie were talking
about, participant burden is something
uh to really think about and minimize uh
time on the clients. So,
um having that for example, demographic
information that comes through uh with
intake and um people could just do that
one time, it would be held in the system
and they wouldn't be asked to do it
again as happened so often in the
[clears throat] medical system.
Um
in in this model uh framework client
reported items are limited to what the
client can can has to tell us. So that
would be intake demographics
um which can be done ahead of time um
before coming to a first appointment and
then um at the end as well. So um
this would be information that's not um
collected through clinical
documentation, outcome measures or
adverse events. Reporting by itself,
potential client reported domains at the
end might include did you feel
respected, understood and supported
through the process. Were your cultural,
spiritual, accessibility or personal
needs appropriately considered? Um, were
there any aspects of your experience
that you find particularly meaningful,
challenging or concerning? And is there
anything else you would like us to know
about your experience?
So, everything else can be reported by
practitioners. Um, and we have some
information categories here. Uh so the
uh the clinical prescriber
uh person would do screening, diagnosis,
eligibility determination, risk
assessment, baseline measures,
uh medical and psychiatric review. Uh
the there's a there's a list of uh all
the kind of data and information that
could uh be recorded by that person. Um
I've divided the assessment and
preparation into two different um um
time points because with this population
with uh the complexity of the what
they're presenting with the screening
and um diagnosis and risk assessment can
be uh lengthy.
For example, doing the suicide scale, if
someone says, "Yes, I have had ideiation
and yes, I have made plans." Um, then
that can very easily with a therapist
turn into a half half the session
exploring that and um similarly with
alcohol use disorder and PTSD. So, um it
seems important to me to um have the
prep session be distinct from that.
Otherwise, it's overtaken by paperwork.
Um the prep the preparatory session um
it's for others to determine whether
that's a therapist, a facilitator, um or
who might be doing that. But the focus
would be on taking information around
goals, intentions, preferences,
boundaries, cultural and spiritual
considerations, um support planning,
hopes, concerns, expectations.
And then the um dosing session
would be um al done by the facilitator
or clinical team. And that would um
include session observations,
accommodations, support, interventions,
notable events, cultural, spiritual
elements that were incorporated such as
what music was used and if there were
ceremonial elements or spiritual
supports.
And then we've um had a lot of talk
about the need for an early follow-up.
That could be a phone call, could be a
session. Um again, we can with a
framework like this, we can fill in um
some of these details as as the
committee can work to fill this in. Um
but uh with early follow-up we'd be
looking at um supporting their needs,
emerging concerns, early reflections,
memories, emotions, insights,
observations, and that kind of
information. Um and then the therapist
uh would be doing the integration
sessions. Uh I guess that could also be
a facilitator. Um and that would be
recording integration themes, meaning
making challenging experiences,
significant life changes
and ongoing needs. Um and then it would
uh the client would be then directed
toward outcome monitoring and that could
be uh contributed to by both the client
and the provider.
um and the outcome measures as Todd and
Addie just went through uh client
feedback with some basic questions.
There's an argument to have some
quantitative open-ended um um
response and feedback as well as answers
to to um survey questions. And then it
would include adverse events, serious
adverse events, longitudinal follow-up
and and quality improvement.
um and then input to the harm reduction
and continuous improvement
loop. So this is a proposed frame to
hang everything on. It's um as we go
[clears throat] forward uh then we can
get more detailed into what is going to
what and who is going to be included at
these different stages.
Uh so that's it from me.
Danielle, I have to say thank you for
taking all of my chicken scratch and
turning it into chicken soup. So, you've
done a fantastic job, y'all team, on
this one. This is absolutely amazing and
I really appreciate that and thanks for
presenting us. Uh, James Brown, awesome
jobs. Just wanted to remind everyone
that if you'd like to participate in any
of the work groups, we would love your
participation and help. Everyone's
welcome and thanks for sharing that. And
so yes, I I want to make sure that
everybody knows that during intersection
work is everybody can participate and
definitely uh Danielle, James and and
Gregory and the teams are working on
these things. So please, you know, reach
out to them to make sure that you're
part of this work in the meantime. And
so I would love now to kind of open it
up to everybody and to share uh
questions, comments, all these kind of
things during this time before we move
on to the next stage which will be kind
of our consensus to adopt this. If you
wouldn't mind, I would love to leave
that up on the screen though and that
way we can have conversations
specifically about that and then we'll
turn that over first question to Gregory
Evans.
>> [clears throat]
>> Um, I was actually just going to request
since Todd and Addie are still here if
they um wanted to
address any like we've been doing this
for some time. here are some gaps that
we see in this framework
and like just if there is any like data
points that you see add value to your
system or maybe gaps that we might and
this off the cuff or whatever but like
um separate from that I wanted to um
honor the question in the chat from Hana
um utilizing the MVC model for capturing
client data and information is something
that I've been thinking about quite a
bit. Um,
and I think that
especially here in New Mexico with how
New Mexico is, how we're approaching
disperate populations, I think this is
something that we want to really hold in
our communications. We want to take the
like and I'm saying we but like I would
advise that we find ways to collect
instrument data that doesn't say this is
a clinical instrument.
Finding a way for the people on the
ground, the individuals to share their
whole selves and just [snorts]
extrapolate that data somehow.
Um, I'd love to talk more about that in
the future, but um, yeah, I just kind of
want to leave that there and give give
the open team space to respond to what
Danielle has put together for us.
>> Yeah, I I c I think it's a yes and
situation. You know, on the one hand,
there is a huge amount of value in being
able to have applesto apples comparisons
on the same validated, you know,
clinical measures across different care
environments and regulatory environments
and, you know, different jurisdictions.
It's really valuable to have harmonized
data and
to
try to
force a person's ineffable experience
into a clinical box is doing that
experience a true injustice. So yes, and
we do need to capture that narrative,
the experience in a client or patients
own words. Um at open we have a couple
of ways of doing this. We do have open
text fields where people can describe
their experience and there has been some
very rich voluntary information that you
know given the opportunity people do
share their experiences. Um that's on
our analysis plan for the next couple of
quarters. Um the other thing is that you
know we we have a mixed methods
approach. So in the Prism study, the the
um NIH funded study, there's an entire
aim that is a mixed methods and
qualitative approach to um do in-depth
interviews and focus groups with uh
clients, their facilitators, their
family members to really get at this,
you know, um individual and relational
experience. Um so I think that's really
important. Um, I would say that there's,
you know, in terms of gaps or, um, you
know, things that you're doing that
we're not doing, um, or vice versa. Um,
that, you know, there there's not a lot
on here that surprises us. Um, you know,
we do get at things like um, [snorts]
uh, therapeutic alliance, um, perceived
harms and benefits, whether we also have
net promoter, whether a person would
recommend their facilitator or service
center. So, um, there's there's not a
lot on here that's surprising and quite
a bit that's complimentary. Um, again,
to to the extent that we could, you
know, support a harmonization, um, that
would be wonderful. Um Todd, I've been
talking for a while. I'm going to turn
it over to you.
>> Thanks and thanks for the opportunity to
comment. Um Danielle, this is just
amazing work and uh open does collect
most of the information categories.
Um, I I would say one gap that New
Mexico stands to really contribute to is
so far in Oregon and Colorado, our our
participants look a lot like the
participants in clinical trials, almost
exclusively
white, well-educated, and wealthy. Um,
and and uh, you know, I see cultural
considerations here. Um boy, I would
love to be able to uh you know build in
or have have you all uh really focus on
you know how um indigenous populations
are accessing this, how this plays out
in a Medicaid population. I think that
would be a huge contribution.
>> Uh that's awesome and I think that's
something that all of our teams are
thinking about actively.
Um [clears throat]
I love the framing of therapeutic
alliance and one of the metrics that I
we've discussed quite a bit in our work
group is how to define the efficacy of
that alliance.
Um yeah I mean just something that
something to think about about regarding
continuous improvement. I mean finding
the right system of ingredients
is yeah
someone needs to measure it.
>> Thanks for those comments and the
sharing of that. That's very valuable. I
appreciate that. I know that James has
his hands up. So we'll move to James.
>> All right. And your mics.
>> Thank you Dan. Um just one comment I
wanted to make for the group just to so
that everybody understands that with
this beautiful thing that Danielle put
together and again thank you Daniellea
Greg Reese for so much of your effort
and time. Um it is client centered focus
for the complete duration of this
process. I think we we we kind of forget
that sometimes and we and we take this
data and we love you know again what if
you collect data what do you do with it
right unless you do something good with
it don't collect it. Um, and so, you
know, it's client- centered focus, and
it doesn't say that throughout this
process, but we wanted to make sure that
everybody understood that in this as a
as a takeaway, but that's all I kind of
wanted to add. Again, thank you so much.
>> Fantastic. Yeah, that's a good point to
bring up and I think some of that that
you're bringing up about the
cliententric focus and the non-violent
communication as Hana mentioned in the
chat uh about and I'll read it in just
so we have it in the record. May I
suggest using nonviolent communication
model of feelings and needs when
capturing client information? For
example, in this model, respect is a
need. Alignment with this model would
look like this. Did you feel safe,
comfortable, and secure during your
treatment? Were your needs for respect,
presence, care, and compassion met
during your session? And I feel that uh
having that you're talking about in this
information capture is kind of like our
our kind of our non-negotiables, the way
that you want to approach this makes a
lot of sense. And I believe that having
that little bit background makes a lot
as you said Danielle also is that uh it
is captured at the point of care by the
best person for that and also try to
capture once and not repeat. So those
are some of the I think foundational
tenants that y'all are talking about
that that exist. Some are written and
some are non-written. I think that uh
putting that into written form makes a
lot of sense. That's that will be our
guidance uh especially for the future.
So that that way we're talking about it
now, but this program will outlive all
of us. And so we need to make sure that
those kind of things are codified at
least in some way that we can capture
keep that too. So thanks for bringing
them up verbally. Let's make sure that
we also have that um in that written
form too. And Brenda, I see your hand is
up.
>> Uh yeah, I want to thank everybody. Uh
this is this is just wonderful
information. Um, as a therapist myself,
I think the best way to gather all this
information is there's going to be parts
of this that are going to feel really
clinical, but it's up to the therapist
to make it not feel so clinical, to make
the, you know, the participant, the
client, the patient comfortable as much
as possible. And I think you know
sentence setting is where uh a big part
of that the environment uh the clinician
or the uh facilitator that's working
with the participant has a lot to do
with making someone feel comfortable not
feel like this is just uh someone in a
white coat coming in with a clipboard
and checking off all the boxes that you
know. Yeah, keeping the information
um as concise and minimal as possible to
make people feel comfortable that this
is not um all about just collecting data
and you know even though that this is
incredibly important because this is
going to affect future generations of
people as well. So and incorporating you
know the cultural aspect of that too you
know having that ingredient of of people
uh volunteering or giving uh their take
on uh writing a little uh like paragraph
on their experience is is a lot for
people because this experience is very
difficult to even verbalize.
I don't know if anybody's ever sat with
anybody or you experienced this yourself
trying to trying to articulate what
you've just experienced is just can be
overwhelming and and this is why um I
think as a clinician I would love to see
what um the intake assessment would be
um h and and present it to a a client
and how that can be as warm and friendly
as possible to make people feel
comfortable. And that is where the
alliance of uh clinician and uh the
participant needs and also too uh the
understanding that you know they're
feeling safe and comfortable and
welcomed into that space is a big one.
So there's a lot of preparation that
goes in before even the the data and
everything is gets collected. However,
this is uh this is what we need. This is
this is still a medical program and I I
I often have to tell and remind people
that this is but we want to make it feel
not like a medical program and I think
that's the whole point of all of this.
Thank you Brent for calling that point
out because it's very true and that's
the reason why as part of the patient
care um the care pathway and safety
group is and patient experience and fit
is so critical and that's why that data
does appear inside of this framework as
well to read some from the comments in
the chat and then I'll jump over to the
hands we've got taught and to might jump
into this also in in this data feedback
is crucial open plans to begin providing
aggregate can't identify clients
summaries of safety and outcomes to
facilitate ators/service centers to
support their ongoing quality
improvement efforts. This was direct
response to community feedback. Eileen
not only that super timeconuming meaning
the data collection and that increases
costs which is the main reason that most
of the data we have is from wealthy
white people. And now we'll jump over to
Addie. You've got your hand up and go
right ahead.
>> Yeah. Um well, uh just a moment to
address Eileen's comment. um in in
Oregon and Colorado, you know, the cost
of services is what's driving the
demographics, not necessarily the cost
of the time for data collection because
we actually, you know, reimburse, we
have remuneration stipens for the for
the research participation. Um you know,
the reason that our demographics are
skewed is because the costs of services
are not within the medical model, not
covered by Medicare, Medicaid, not
covered by insurance. Um, but I I really
wanted to reiterate something that that
Brenda talked about, which is, you know,
this um the patient participant client
burden. Um, and so much of that
compassionate care comes around the
timing of all of this, right? When do
you complete these baseline and
follow-up surveys? And um the you know
when we have our community engagement
officers who are working directly with
facilitators to try and find the ideal
timing to work all of this into their
workflow. One of the really key best
practices is don't do anything but the
administration on the administration
day. Right? So anything that's going to
happen that's related to research or
quality improvement or data collection
or intake that is not that's all going
to happen during the preparation phase.
well ahead of an administration to
really set aside that time um as
something you know that that's very
clientup supported.
Um same thing on the other end of things
you know we don't um reach out to people
until a minimum one week after their
administration because that's a very
critical window that people are you know
still uh processing their experience. Um
so you know that oneweek followup while
there are really important safety
questions and satisfaction questions um
we are you know incredibly respectful of
this what could be a disruptive or
transformational or you know um
important experience for folks. Um,
interestingly for, you know, all the
rest of our follow-up time points, we've
recently done a retention study. You
know, as Todd mentioned, our retention
rate is at 87% or so at all the time
points. And we were like very curious
about why why is it so much better than
your standard study. Um, and what we're
finding is people are using the surveys
as integration.
So, it's a part they're considering, you
know, all of these follow-up time points
as a part of their continual checking in
on their ongoing process. Um, and you
know, it's able to put their other life
events into context and say, well, I'm
having a hard time answering these
questions because all this stuff is
happening in the world and I'm
distracted or I went through a major
life transition. So, it's really, you
know, um the the the it it although it I
think it's helpful to be considerate of
um client burden in terms of, you know,
um all of the questions that we're that
we're asking of them. Um it is at the
same time doing them a service in terms
of facilitating their integration and
reflection on their experiences.
>> Beautiful. Thank you very much. And
thought dropped into the chat also. are
getting ready to publish results from
qualitative interviews about
integration. Clients report that
answering research questions were an
opportunity to further reflection and
integration as well. And Craig, you got
your hand up as well, so we'll move to
you.
Todd, I'm very eager to read that.
Um,
a couple things. Something and and a
like feel free to cap me if I go over
five minutes or whatever here, but
Oh, I see you have the cards, Dan.
>> I always [laughter] need the cards for
you here. I I I'm prepared for you all
the time,
>> my hero. Okay. So, um I'm going to
disclose some information here that I've
been like trying to figure out the right
time to disclose to the committees or
whatever, but um I wanted to start with
something that Brenda said and and
describing the ineffable, right? And so
I I come from a rare population of
psychedelic nerds that in the '9s chose
to do detailed experimentation on
themselves and report self-report trip
reports to Arrowid.
These [clears throat] are not
normal behaviors. [laughter] Most people
don't have that type of patience or
dedication. But we're finding that
people that choose to be engaged in self
care in the psychedelic space are
utilizing
psychedelics for self-care, betterment
of self
um do have that kind of wherewithal and
and that grows to some extent. So I'm
not surprised to see the retention.
I'm very happy to see the data that
shows the retention that I assume.
Um, and as far as the impact on
the patient and the practitioner, I'm h
having to like extrapolate all this
data. I've recently aligned myself with
company who's um I think James was in
here earlier. Company's called Ignite
Synergy. I think we're going through a
rebrand.
I think something happened with your
mic.
>> Craig. Craig, I think I muted yourself.
>> Okay. Yeah, I did.
>> I was leaning. Um, so Okay. So, I jump I
jumped into a company called Ignite
Synergy. We're going through a rebrand,
so there'll be a new name to that soon.
But essentially what it is is a it's an
agentic system care client- centered
data sovereign system where instead of
the practitioners holding the data
the platform holds the data and allows
the participants or people or humans
that are the end points of that of that
program to consent to their data being
used by their psychiatrist, their
movement coach, whatever part of their
care their their their overarching care
team they choose to consent that data
to.
What I think that this system
could potentially have the ability to do
is through
AI models,
extreme aggressive consent
um
where for on the patient side to to
simply extrapolate that data.
[clears throat] And the idea is that the
patient can come on before they have a
practitioner. And this is a tool that
can follow them through 5, 10, 15, 20
years and be that space that they go
back to for their self integration, a
patient can build their own integration
plan and introduce that to their
practitioner as opposed to the other way
around.
And so that way when I decide that I'm
not aligned with this therapist and I
want to move to this therapist, my
practice continues. And if I go into a
regulated system like a medical
psilocybin program, that's just a
singular pathway among many that I that
I could um follow through through
through my journey.
>> So um I want to talk about that more but
um for another day, but I think it's a
solution to a lot of the problems that
we're talking about.
>> Appreciate it. Thank you very much. I'm
going to actually Danielle's got her
hand up and this is a perfect time to
kind of bring this about full circle
since we've heard the comments from
everybody on on this client work for
information capture the reporting
framework. Uh Danielle, this is your
kind of last like wrap us up and take us
home on this.
>> Um all right. Uh yes, I just had a
question um for the for the committee.
Uh one of the things we've added in here
is the assessment and eligibility is an
extra step or an extra session. uh
that's because of this particular
population and the complexity of their
presentations.
Um I just want to know what people
thought about that because it does
extend the process. Um and just in
response to everyone on the client
burden um in this model, the client is
mainly doing the intake uh part of of
the reporting, which is something
clients are going to do anyway for um
with a therapist. uh and and that's
where we'd capture the demographics and
then um the rest of the burden is really
will be reported by by the care team. So
it's very light for [clears throat]
them. Um, and then also having that
assessment be separate allows the
preparation to be more meaningful and
more um in the spirit of the the journey
that they're about to take rather than
needing to ask about um you know their
the their history of um mental health.
So uh I would like to know what people
think about is that going to be too much
too many sessions or is that
what do people think
>> and so you know the referral and entry
can be done even outside of the uh or
are you saying with the provider or the
referring provider? So that
>> yeah that's usually done online before
you come in
most of that and then the assessment a
lot of that can be done online before
you come in the baselines but there are
things like the audit for alcohol or the
suicide screening there's some things
that you need to be um assessed in with
a clinician um yeah
>> and there are certain and you're exactly
right because in the system there might
be a person holding multiple roles
uh in this and so that might or there
might be a a a physical space in which
multiple roles are physically located in
that space and so it might make it easy
to go from one to the other also. So
that might shrink down that a little bit
as well, but that's what I think. Um
>> yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So
>> um yeah. All right. Well, thank you.
That's that was that was my question.
>> Yeah. Thank you. And just before before
Todd and Adrian jump off here, um Todd
will circulate when to change or improve
myself as the second most common reason
people in a study report as a reason for
engaging in services. Curiosity is the
top reason. Todd will circulate the
report when published. We're not quite
ready. Analysis ongoing, but I'm sure
the lead author would be willing to
present preliminary results prior to
publication at a later point in time.
And Addy, folks, thank you for
invitation to join me to transition to
the response. Thank you very much.
Welcome. Wonderful questions and
conversations. And Eileen, wouldn't the
narrative of experience be a client
burden? I recognize this isn't part of
the documentation discussion, but
something that was brought up in the
gap. Obviously, those qualitative
experience would be valuable though.
Thank you. So now that we've kind of
come to this, I do want to see if we can
from our group. Uh again, we want to
kind of come to a consensus. I would
like to take this to our our board as a
whole. Uh as what we wanted to move
forward with our first milestone out of
this committee. And so for those of you
that are on the committee call now that
you're in New Mexico and if you've
already done your introductions and
reported any kind of of affiliations or
things like that, please join us then in
uh calling for a vote. And so when we do
the vote, I just ask for you to raise
your hand. Um so for those of you that
would like to come to consensus taking
what Danielle and his team has prevented
presented for client workflow
information capture which is reporting
framework for our first milestone please
raise your hand or if you have any
comments then place them into the chat
but we'll move over for moving forward
raise your hand to move this forward.
I have three hands. I'll leave it for
just a moment.
Okay. And if we might lower the hands,
please.
And then we'll move to the second part
of the question. Is there anybody that
does not want to move this forward as
our first milestone out of committee?
and you would raise your hand the same
way.
I zero hands at this time.
Okay, thank you very much for that.
Appreciate it. And Danielle and team
really appreciate all of this. This is
wonderful first uh like the first
milestone to get out of this workg group
and that I'm happy to take and present
to the board as a whole for our first
milestone here. Amazing. And again, this
is this is beautiful to to tape to them.
So, thank you very much. Hey. Hey, we
did a I know. Yes. Yes. I think Hey,
there we go. I love it. And our next uh
just to kind of give everybody a little
bit of preparation for the next
milestone that we'll be working on with
the intercession group. And Danielle,
uh, I would appreciate if you want and
anybody else that is on the workg group,
the intercession workg group, drop your
email in the chat so that people can get
a hold of you if they want to join y'all
for this because again, this is the work
that happens between the committee and
at the committee. Then we discuss and
talk about and work on. So just so you
know, please join them as they do some
of this work that we come back to this
committee to present. Uh, there's a lot
of work to get done. We cannot do it all
in these two-hour sessions. So what you
see on the screen right now is our next
uh set of milestones and it's going to
be the uh quality improvement harm
reduction framework. And so taking the
reporting framework that Danielle and
team have presented. This is what we're
looking at for each one of the work
groups uh to kind of take on and to
really talk about what is the what are
those kind of reporting events that we
need to worry about for uh adverse
reporting or client best fit and some of
the data that we need to be able to
track qualitatively quantitatively as
well. Uh that is our next uh RACI work
group that will be present July 10th
from 9 to 11 here. So that'll be our
next month's presentation. Uh and so
these are some of the ideas that I just
kind of gathered and put together for
those teams that uh kind of have those
specific roles and responsibilities. Uh
but of course what we get to hear is
like I said taking this chicken scratch
and turning it into something amazing.
So really appreciate um for y'all in the
workg groupoups doing that and taking it
right back to something here that we can
digest and work on. So in the chat
you'll see Danielle Leonards and Gregory
Evans emails. So, please reach out to
one of them, both of them to make sure
that you're part of that intersection
group. And again, our kind of timeline
that we're looking at here for u the
other work groups, we've already got
these on the calendar. Make sure that
you sign up for these presentations and
these times. So, again, we've today is
the June 12th, we've worked on reporting
framework consensus and move that
forward. uh our next one again July 10th
for the harm reduction and quality
improvement framework and that will be
followed by our August 7th meeting which
will be the core extended data set
framework and we'll have consensus then
and so we do have on the calendar
September 11th as one of our holder
places for our meetings so that we can
then have one of our last ones before we
can really kind of see where we go
direction from here the other work
groups uh Brenda's group will have uh
some a lot of stuff that will come out
from there. So, we want to make sure
what comes out of some of the other work
groups is incorporated into ours. So,
that's like I said just a little bit of
an upcoming I appreciate uh thank you
very much uh Johnny for putting in
here's the link where you can find the
upcoming meetings and James Brown
dropped in the chat uh his email address
as well. So, thank you for being part of
the intersection groups. So at this time
uh number one we have to celebrate again
that uh uh Danielle and team have
created something our first milestone
that we voted on got consensus on and we
will take to our uh board as a whole and
appreciate that. That's huge for for for
me to to see that this is something that
u we have come up with as as as a as a
wonderful um presentation going forward
with what build our work here. So, thank
you very much for doing that. Again,
this is what I was hoping that we could
use this committee for is to do amazing
work here. So, we move into our public
comment time. Uh, as we go into public
comment time, we have three minutes for
anybody that would like to share
anything at this time. Uh, again, what
we do during public comment time is you
just raise your hand and we will call on
you and, uh, we'll unmute your
microphone and you have three minutes to
share. So, anybody [clears throat]
that's willing to do any public comments
or anything, please do so. Now,
>> while you're raising your hands, we've
got Sky Rivers. Thank you all for a
great meeting once again. Wonderful
work.
I'm still going to hold for any hands
for public comment. Uh while I'm doing
that, I again will uh share that uh
Brenda Bard's meeting is at 1:00. Don't
forget if you're going to be free during
that time. Please join Brenda and her
meeting. Uh Danielle, I saw that you
unmuted. Go ahead.
U sorry that was an accident. Sorry.
and I'll hold for just a little bit, but
uh just in case uh you do have anything
that you'd like to share, please again
raise your hand. But if not, uh we
appreciate your time here today. Uh
seriously, we really appreciate the
presentation from Todd and Addie. Thank
you very much for being here and sharing
that information with us. We hope to
hear more, of course, from you all as we
go. And uh really thank you so much for
taking part of your Friday for being
with us on this. And uh again the
amazing work that y'all are doing uh
like I said behind these meetings um is
is very appreciated. So thank you. Uh
and if there is no other comment then
y'all just have a wonderful weekend. I
hope it's a wonderful weekend for you
and we'll see you again here on June
July 10th.
And on behalf of the Department of
Health, thank you everybody for joining
on in. Have a great weekend.
>> Thank you.